#### Contact

gemcristobal@hotmail.com

www.linkedin.com/in/lydiacristobal (LinkedIn)

# Top Skills

Nursing

Music

Recording

# Languages

Tagalog

#### Certifications

Congress 2020 Poster Presenter Board certified in advanced nurse

executive practice

Licensed nursing home administrator

**Board Certified in Gerontology** 

#### Honors-Awards

Living Legends Advanced Leadership Scholarship Award

#### **Publications**

Managing Care Transitions in Long-Term Care

# Dr. Lydia Alicia Cristobal DNP, LNHA, RN-BC, NEA-BC

Administrator at CarePoint Health System

Hasbrouck Heights, New Jersey

# Summary

Experienced in healthcare of civilian, federal and military institutions. Board certified in advanced nurse executive practice and in gerontology. Licensed nursing home administrator in New Jersey.

Acknowledged for efficient work, while providing good leadership for team success. A multi-tasker, able to adapt to different situations to accomplish the mission in a proficient manner. Confident with warm communication style. Other attributes: excellent communicator; strategic planner; thrives on rapid change; passion for success; good in integration, collaboration and implementation; creative negotiator; flexible; passion for educational enrichment and training.

# Experience

CarePoint Health System

Administrator

January 2018 - Present (2 years 7 months)

Bayonne Medical Center and Hoboken University Medical Center Hospitals

Direct the day to day operations of the transitional care unit of Bayonne and Hoboken hospitals in accordance with current federal, state, and local standards, guidelines and regulations that govern long-term care facilities to assure that the highest degree of quality care can be provided. Reports directly to the Chief Hospital Executive.

Bayonne Medical Center Administrative Supervisor June 2011 - Present (9 years 2 months) Bayonne, NJ Responsible for the clinical supervision of patient care and represents hospital management on the assigned shift to ensure the delivery of quality patient care for a 278-bed hospital.

Revised administrative report form to improve documentation and to increase supervisor productivity.

United States Army Reserve Major December 1999 - Present (20 years 8 months) Picatinny Arsenal, New Jersey

Case manager of 7245th Medical Support Unit

Former officer-in-charge (O-5 position) of the 7415th Troop Medical Clinic with mission to assist with Soldier Readiness Processing in accordance with the USAMEDCOM mobilization plan. Accountable for the 5 sections assigned: Primary care, pharmacy, mental health, preventive medicine, and dental, totaling to 61 healthcare professional soldiers assigned. Responsible for day to day operations and readiness to include S1 personnel, S3 training, S4 supply and finance, 24h soldier accountability, medical and deployable readiness, counseling evaluations, physical fitness training, Equal Opportunity Program, SHARP program, suicide prevention, family readiness group, additional duty programs, security clearances, leader development program, and general good order and discipline of the unit

Former Officer-In-Charge of 90th and 311th Military History Detachment, military historian

Medical-Surgical Nurse - 66H, qualified Public Affairs Officer - 46A

Ulchi Freedom Guardian 2014 in Korea: Officer-in-charge of a public affairs team consisting of one officer and six soldiers to publish journal articles, photojournalism, and broadcasting products. Also worked as the public affairs officer in G33, Combat Operations and Intelligence Center to brief battle or commander updates.

Earned Army Achievement Medal for saving the life of a Korean national in clinical shock and distress through emergency medical treatment while in the plane en route to Korea from Chicago.

Served as training officer of 361st Public Affairs Operation Center (PAOC).

Former clinical ICU nurse at the 405th Combat Support Hospital.

Earned Army Achievement Medal for successfully transitioning 99% of nursing assistants (91B) and LPNs(91C) to combat medics (68W) and implemented sustainment training to remain fully qualified.

Veteran of Operation Enduring Freedom

BrightStar Care
Director Of Nursing
November 2017 - September 2018 (11 months)
Greater New York City Area

Responsible for the overall direction of home health clinical services, including responsibility for the quality, adequacy of services provided, and supervision of staff. Establishes, implements, and evaluates goals and objectives for home health services that meet and promote the standards of quality. Assures that care is coordinated between services and that all of the client's needs are identified through the assessment process and addressed through the implementation of the Plan of Care and supervisory process.

Memorial Hermann Health System Senior Project Manager November 2015 - June 2017 (1 year 8 months) Houston, Texas Area

Responsible for managing small to large scale projects in support of hospital business objectives.

Nurse researcher and promotes evidence-based practice (EBP) through management of EBP council, nursing grand rounds, continuing education planning and implementation in preparation for Magnet accreditation.

Nurse educator and lectures for the Memorial Hermann System's (14 acutecare hospitals) nurse residency program.

Successfully improved outpatient diabetes program by increasing patient visits through project management and revised policy and guidelines.

Initiated the Center for Nursing Excellence Journal and as editor-in-chief for nurses to share their experiential learning through exemplar writing for reflective practice and improve education through sharing academic work.

Accountable for the EBP projects of the nurse residents to assist in project development, manuscript preparation for publication, and poster presentation.

Initiated and headed a system nursing research to determine the effectiveness of nursing education for acute kidney injury prevention.

Created, directed, and edited the system's acute kidney injury prevention educational film to improve nursing education and implement strategic interventions to decrease the rates of acute kidney injuries.

Initiated monthly research clinics and program curriculum to improve nurses' knowledge and skills in conducting nursing research.

Lutheran Medical Center
Patient Services Coordinator
June 2011 - November 2013 (2 years 6 months)
Brooklyn, NY

Responsible for all the nursing operations and patient services of the ambulatory care family health clinic: medical, pediatrics, obstetrics, gynecology, back specialty, podiatry, gastroenterology, neurology, cardiology, and endocrinology.

Collaborates with the site director and medical director in clinic operations to improve core measures by achieving desired target goals.

Created new systems in place to increase work productivity such as restructured the nursing assignments, staff accountability and ownership in projects.

Assisted in maintaining deficiency-free status during Joint Commission on the Accreditation of Healthcare Organizations (JCAHO) inspection.

Created the provider evaluation tool for medical assistants that became network-wide use.

Increased post-partum visits from 47% to 100% through the creation and implementation of quality assurance log, while improving interdisciplinary communication.

Eastwick College

Nursing Educator

January 2011 - October 2012 (1 year 10 months)

Nursing educator for Mental Health/ Psychiatric Nursing, Med-Surg and NCLEX Review

**Access Nursing Services** 

RN

October 2010 - February 2011 (5 months)

RN home care, chart review, case management

Care-One

Assistant Administrator, RN-BC

January 2010 - October 2010 (10 months)

Responsible for assisting the Administrator in the day to day coordination and oversight of the 134-bed sub-acute Livingston, NJ facility in accordance with current federal, state and local standards, guidelines, and regulations that govern long-term care facilities to assure that the highest degree of quality care can be provided to the patients and residents at all times. Reports directly to the Regional Director of Operations in the absence of the Administrator.

Lincoln Park Renaissance

**Assistant Administrator** 

August 2009 - January 2010 (6 months)

Accountable for 159-bed long-term care/ rehabilitation facility. Plans for, supervises, and evaluates supervisors assigned to shifts in order to meet the total needs of the patient and to maintain the quality of service. Accountable for monthly clinical report, quality assurance/ quality management and operations of the nursing department. Assists the administrator in managing other departments: rehab, social service, maintenance, housekeeping, recreation and food service. Started as assistant director of nursing then promoted to clinical director of a 60-bed sub-acute facility until promoted again as assistant administrator.

MedStat, LLC

Health Care Coordinator September 2008 - September 2009 (1 year 1 month)

Administers measles, mumps and rubella vaccine to admitting college students in Metropolitan College of New York. Mentors 2 New York University nursing students for leadership training and to improve nursing skills. Per diem status.

# Veterans Affairs Medical Center LPN

May 2001 - March 2008 (6 years 11 months)

LPN duties in a medical-surgical 40-bed unit. Provided effective in-services training and mentoring to staff that led to improved performance evaluations and patient outcomes. Supervised and trained nursing assistants to improve patient care. Member of the 7C unit homepage committee to develop and improve our unit's communication, education resources and team cohesion to serve as the model to other units. Member of the Bar Code Medication Administration Committee to collaborate with the IT, pharmacy and other nursing units in improving the BCMA software to increase patient safety and efficiency in nursing productivity and pharmacy communication. In-charge of organizing and maintaining medication and treatment carts to improve efficiency in medication and treatment pass. Advocated for patients that resulted in improved patient outcomes. Received 3-month leadership training and acted as facilitator of team building in unit. Accurately documents transfer assessments and patient progress in compliance to regulations that resulted in efficiency of care. Participates in interdisciplinary team meeting to evaluate patient progress. Preceptor to new employees in ward. Started the "Lunch and Learn" program by empowering the nursing staff for improved team cohesion and collaboration through education training.

Tandem Management Company Charge Nurse/ Unit Manager August 1993 - January 2007 (13 years 6 months)

Unit manager for 45-bed unit of sub-acute and long term care in Prospect Heights Care Center, including MDS, utilization review, and daily meeting with department heads to discuss and resolve issues. Charge nurse for 60-bed unit of hospice and long-term care in Regent Care Center. Assisted in the chart auditing process and resolved issues, which resulted in a deficiency-free state inspection of Prospect Heights Care Center in 2005. Decreased amount of fall incidents by 90% by implementing additional investigative tool and accountability. Provided effective staff training and mentoring to staff that led to improved performance evaluations, team cohesion and patient outcomes.

# Heights Health Care Agency

LPN

July 2004 - May 2005 (11 months)

Agency per diem staff LPN assigned to several nursing homes such as Christian Health Care, Manhattan View Health Care and Veterans Affairs Long-term Care.

# Rego Park Nursing Home

LPN

October 1993 - August 1995 (1 year 11 months)

Part-time staff LPN

# Fair Lawn Manor Nursing Home

LPN

April 1993 - August 1993 (5 months)

First opportunity to work as staff LPN right after graduation from practical nursing school.

# Education

Yale University

Doctor of Nursing Practice, Leadership and Health Policy (2013 - 2016)

New York University

MS, Nursing Administration · (2009 - 2013)

New York University

BS, Nursing · (2007 - 2009)

University of Phoenix

BSHA/LTC, Healthcare Administration in Long-Term Care · (2006 - 2009)

Bergen Community College

Nursing · (1997 - 2000)